[警报声]
[ALARM BLARING]
- 相位炮待命 - 距离43,000，正在接近。
- Phaser banks standing by. - Range 43,000 and closing.
- 你读到了什么，史波克先生? - 配置不详。
- What do you read, Mr. Spock? - Configuration unidentified.
离子推进，高速，但是是一种独特的技术。
Ion propulsion, high velocity, though of a unique technology.
- 能联系上吗？- 已尝试所有语言，没有回应
- Any contact? - All languages attempted, no response.
- 使用标准星际音标 - 继续试
- Using standard interstellar symbols. - Keep trying.
- 放大10倍，契科夫先生 - 是，长官
- Magnification 10, Mr. Chekov. - Aye, sir.
距离3,800，正在接近
Thirty-eight thousand and closing.
- 斯科提，你怎么看？- 我不知道，但她不美吗？
- Well, Scotty? - Beats me, but isn't she a beauty?
- 有趣的设计 - 还有离子推进器
- Interesting design. - And ion propulsion, at that.
他们可以教我们一两招
They could teach us a thing or two.
- 生命体呢，史波克先生? - 有一个。人形或类似的
- Life-forms, Mr. Spock? - One. Humanoid or similar.
活动水平低，生命维持系统正常运作。
Low level of activity, life-support systems functioning.
内部大气：常规的氮-氧组合
Interior atmosphere: conventional nitrogen-oxygen.
仪器显示从生命体中发出了传送光束，
Instruments indicate a transferal beam emanating from the life-form,
瞄准了企业号的舰桥
directed at the bridge of the Enterprise.
- 警卫 - 警卫到舰桥上
- Security guard. - Security guard to the bridge.
我是詹姆斯·柯克舰长。这里是星舰企业号
I'm Captain James Kirk. This is the starship Enterprise.
柯克：宇宙，最后的边疆
KIRK: Space, the final frontier.
这些是星舰企业号的航程。
These are the voyages of the starship Enterprise.
它的五年任务：探索未知的新世界，
Its five-year mission: To explore strange new worlds,
寻找新的生命和新的文明，
to seek out new life and new civilizations,
勇敢地航向前人未至之境。
to boldly go where no man has gone before.
- 发生什么事了? - 船舵状态，苏鲁先生。
- What happened? - Helm status, Mr. Sulu.
- 较上次读数没有变化 - 所有甲板的情况报告
- No change from last reading. - Condition reports from all decks.
史波克，史波克在哪儿？
Spock. Where's Spock?
- 麦考伊：吉姆？吉姆？ - 什么事？
- McCoy: Jim? Jim? - Yes, what is it?
- 你最好现在来医务室 - 好的，我这就去。
- You'd better come to Sickbay now.
- All right. On my way.
5号甲板。人员，无损坏。
Deck 5. Personnel, no damage.
现在
Now.
运作
Functioning.
天啊
My God.
- 史波克。怎么了？- 我发现他躺在手术台上
- Spock. What happened? - I found him on the table.
- 像这样？- 不，不是这样
- Like this? - No, not like this.
发生什么了？- 我不知道
- What happened? - I don't know.
你给他用上了完整的生命维持系统。他死了吗？
You've got him on complete life-support. Was he dead?
他比死还糟糕
He was worse than dead.
- 你什么意思？- 吉姆...
- What do you mean? - Jim...
说吧。有什么神秘的？
Come on. What's the mystery?
- 他的大脑不见了 - 他的大脑？
- His brain is gone. - His brain?
它被手术切除了
It's been removed surgically.
- 他是怎么活下来的？- 这是我见过的最好的技术活儿
- How could he survive? - It's the best technical job I've seen.
每个神经末梢都被整齐地封住。没有撕裂，也没有扯断。
Every nerve ending was neatly sealed. Nothing ripped, nothing torn.
没有出血。简直是医学奇迹
No bleeding. It's a medical miracle.
如果大脑不见了，那么史波克就快死了
If the brain is missing, then Spock is dying.
没有
No.
那令人难以置信的瓦肯人的体格一直坚持到生命维持系统接手
That incredible Vulcan physique hung on till the life-support cycle took over.
他的身体活着。自助功能还在继续
His body lives. The autonomic functions continue.
但没有思维
But there is no mind.
- 那个女孩 - 是的
- That girl. - Aye.
- 什么女孩？- 那艘船上的
- What girl? - From that ship.
她拿走了
She took it.
我不知道为什么，或在哪里，但她一定把它拿走了
I don't know why, or where, but she must have taken it.
老骨头，你能让他维持多久？
Bones, how long can you keep him functioning?
- 我不能保证 - 那还不够
- I can't guarantee. - That's not good enough.
如果这种事情发生在我们任何一个人身上，我会说是无限期的。
If it happened to any of us, I would say indefinitely.
但是瓦肯人的生理学限制了我能做的
But Vulcan physiology limits what I can do.
史波克的身体依靠那个巨大的大脑维持生命
Spock's body is dependent on that tremendous brain for life-support.
那我们就得带上他
Then we'll have to take him with us.
- 带他去哪儿？- 找他的大脑，医生
- Take him where? - In search of his brain, Doctor.
照你说的，一旦我们找到大脑，必须把它装回他的身体
From what you say, the moment we find it we must restore it to his body.
吉姆
Jim.
你打算去哪儿找？
Where are you going to look?
在这整个星系里，你打算去哪儿找史波克的大脑？
In this whole galaxy, where are you going to look for Spock's brain?
你打算怎么找到它？
How are you going to find it?
- 我会找到的 - 就算你找到了，我也没法修复
- I'll find it. - Even if you do, I can't restore it.
我没有这样的医学技术
I don't have the medical technique.
它被拿走了，它就可以放回去
It was taken out. It can be put back in.
但我不知道怎么做
But I don't know how.
偷它的贼知道，我会逼她说出来
The thief that took it has the knowledge. I'll force it out of her.
如果没能在24小时内找到，你最好忘记整件事
If you don't find it in 24 hours, you'd better forget the whole thing.
你和斯科提。让史波克准备好
You and Scotty. Have Spock ready.
我又找到了。她那艘飞船的离子轨迹
I've got it again. An ion trail from that ship of hers.
- 轨迹通向哪儿？- 西格玛龙系
- Where does the trail lead? - System Sigma Draconis.
- 最大速度 - 曲速6
- Maximum speed. - Warp 6.
- 轨迹没有错误吧？ - 没问题，长官
- No question about the trail? - No mistake, sir.
柯克：舰长日志，星历5431.4
KIRK: Captain's log, stardate 5431.4.
我们已经跟踪那艘载有史波克大脑的飞船15小时20分钟了
For 15 hours and 20 minutes, we have followed the ship that has Spock's brain.
留给我们的时间还有：8小时40分钟
Time left to us: eight hours and 40 minutes.
- 我跟丢了 - 所有扫描仪，极限搜查
- I've lost the trail. - All scanners, extreme sweep.
是，长官
Aye, sir.
- 怎么样？ - 完全没信号，舰长
- Well? - No signal at all, Captain.
- 它不见了，突然消失了 -我们跟丢了。
- It's gone. A sudden deaction shift. - We've lost her trail.
但她进入了那个星系
But she went into that system.
把西格玛龙系的示意图放在屏幕上。
Put a schematic of Sigma Draconis on the screen.
是，舰长
Aye, Captain.
解读一下，契科夫先生
Read-out, Mr. Chekov?
恒星，光谱类型，伽马9，有九个行星。
Sun, spectral type, Gamma 9, nine planets.
据报告其中三个为M级，拥有智慧生命。
Three of them Class-M, possessing sapient life according to reports.
她呼吸我们的空气，她一定在其中一个上
She was breathing our air. She must have gone to one of them.
给我们看三颗M级行星，契科夫先生
Show us the three Class-M planets, Mr. Chekov.
左边的那个，编号为三，在工业规模评级为B。
The one on the left, number III, rates letter B on the industrial scale.
相当1485年的地球
Earth equivalent, approximately 1485.
是的，长官。第二颗，M级，编号四，评级为G
Yes, sir. Second planet, Class-M, number IV, rates letter G.
2030年
The year 2030.
那艘船要么领先我们很多年，要么侥幸有不可思议的设计。
That ship was many years ahead of us or the most incredible design fluke.
- 第三颗M级行星呢？- 编号六。没有工业发展
- Third Class-M planet? - Number VI. No industrial development.
最后报告，，处于冰川时代。智慧生命很多，但处于最原始的水平
Last report, in a glacial age. Sapient life plentiful, but on a most primitive level.
据我所知，这三颗M级行星
As I understand it, there are three Class-M planets.
都没有能力发射星际飞行器，然而有一个做到了
Not one is capable of launching an interstellar flight, yet one did.
- 是的，长官 - 谢谢
- Yes, sir. - Thank you.
我在六号行星上发现了高能量的产生
I'm picking up high energy generation on planet VI.
那是原始的冰川行星。能量源？
That's the primitive glaciated planet. The source?
它可能是自然现象。火山活动，蒸汽，各种原因
It could be natural. Volcanic activity, steam, any number of causes.
- 它是有规律的 - 地表读数显示什么？
- It's regular. - What do surface readings show?
没有组织的文明。不规则间隔的原始人形生物
No organized civilization. Primitive humanoids at irregular intervals.
- 生成能量的脉冲？ - 我无法解释，长官
- Pulsations of generated energy? - I can't explain it, sir.
我不能猜错
I can't afford to guess wrong.
最好选择正确的星球，到那儿找到大脑
Better choose the right planet, get there, find the brain.
8小时35分钟
Eight hours and 35 minutes.
- 建议？ - 西格玛龙系三号
- Recommendations? - Sigma Draconis III.
- 它最近，人口最多 - 但技术评级是3
- It's closest, heaviest population. - But a technological rating of 3.
- 它不能把飞船送入太空 - 这些星球都不能
- It couldn't put that ship into space. - None of these planets could.
要我说是四号行星。技术上它领先于三号行星
I say planet IV. It's ahead of planet III technologically.
但先进的离子推进器甚至超过了我们的能力
But advanced ion propulsion beyond even our capabilities.
他们要 史波克 先生的大脑干什么? 有什么用？
What would they want with Mr. Spock's brain? What use is it?
- 他们为什么要它？ - 是啊，他们为什么想要它呢？
- Why do they want it? - Yes, why would they want it?
8小时34分钟
Eight hours and 34 minutes.
你说，六号行星是冰川化的？
Planet VI is glaciated, you say?
至少几千年了。只有热带地区是无冰的
For several thousand years at least. Only the tropical zone is ice-free.
但是能量。有规律。就是那儿
But the energy. Regular. It's there.
- 真的 - 这说不通，但它就在那儿
- It's real. - It doesn't make sense, but it's there.
传送室，待命。我要带一支登陆小队去六号行星
Transporter room, stand by. I'm taking a landing party to Planet VI.
好的，长官
Aye, aye, sir.
直觉，舰长？
A hunch, Captain?
直觉，苏鲁先生
A hunch, Mr. Sulu.
但如果你猜错了呢，舰长？
But if you guess wrong, Captain?
如果我猜错了，史波克先生就死了
If I guess wrong, Mr. Spock is dead.
史波克会死
Spock will die.
柯克：舰长日志，星历4351.5
KIRK: Captain's log, stardate 4351.5.
我们正传送去西格玛龙星系的一颗冰川化的行星
We are beaming to a glaciated planet in the Sigma Draconis star system.
留给我们寻找史波克大脑的时间还剩：8小时29分钟
Time left for us to find Spock's brain: eight hours and 29 minutes.
宇航服温度72
Suit temperatures are 72.
生命体读数，史波克先生？Scott先生？
Life-form readings, Mr. Spock? Mr. Scott?
零散分布，间距大。类人，大方向上
Scattered, widely spaced. Humanoid, all right. On the large side.
小心。我们知道他们的发展很原始
Watch out. We know their development is primitive.
读数？
Read-out?
没有建筑物，没有我能读到的机械物体
No structures, no mechanized objects I can read.
表面没有能量消耗或产生
No surface consumption or generation of energy.
大气当然没问题。温度最高40，适宜居住
Atmosphere is all right, of course. Temperature maximum of 40. Livable.
你皮真厚
You have a thick skin.
斯科提：舰长！
SCOTTY: Captain!
岩石丛里有人
There's someone out there in the rocks.
- 五个人形大个子 - 相位枪击晕模式
- Five of them. Humanoid. Large. - Phasers on stun.
我希望他们神志清醒
I want them conscious.
等我信号开火
Fire only on my signal.
侧翼包抄。
Flank out.
契科夫
Chekov.
[大声叫]
[MEN SHOUT]
我们对你们没有恶意。我们不是你的敌人，我们是你的朋友
We mean you no harm. We're not your enemies, we're your friends.
我们只想和你谈谈
We only wish to talk to you.
你们... 不是其他人吗？
You... are not the others?
不，我们来自遥远的地方
No. We come from a far place.
我们是人
We are men.
- 人？ - 就像你们一样
- Men? - Like yourselves.
你们很小，就像其他人一样
You are small. Like the others.
- 谁是其他人？- 痛苦给予者
- Who are the others? - Givers of pain.
和喜悦
And delight.
他们和你一起生活在这儿吗？
Do they live here with you?
不，他们会来。给予痛苦和喜悦
No. They come. They give pain and delight.
- 他们是从天上来的吗？- 他们就在这儿
- Do they come from the sky? - They are here.
你会见到的
You will see.
其他人会来找你们的
The others will come for you.
他们为所有像我们一样的人来
They come for all like us.
他们也是冲着你们的女人来的吗？
Do they come for your women as well?
- 女人？- 和你同种族的女性
- Women? - The female of your kind.
你的话说不通
Your words say nothing.
你没有配偶吗？
Don't you have a mate?
- 配偶？- 同伴
- Mate? - A companion.
- 你能带我们去找其他人吗？- 没人想去找他们
- Will you take us to find the others? - No one wants to find them.
我们想找到他们。带上我们，我们就放你走
We want to find them. Take us and we'll let you go.
舰长，那个方向500米有个地下基地
Captain. 500 meters in that direction is a foundation under the surface.
- 到处都是标记 - 建筑物呢？
- The registration's all over the place. - Buildings?
被埋了，但它们曾经在这儿 - 那下面是其他人住的地方
- Buried, but they were here once. - Down there is where the others live.
- 看看能不能找到下去的路 - 不！
- See if you can find a way down. - No!
- 别去那！别！别！ - 没事的
- Do not go there! No! No! - It's all right.
没关系。让他走
It's all right. Let him go.
- 他们做了什么让你如此恐惧?-他说了什么? 痛苦和喜悦？
- What do they do to cause such terror? - What did he say? Pain and delight?
- 奇怪的混合体 - 一个死亡的被埋葬的城市
- Peculiar mixture. - A dead and buried city
在一个冰川时代的行星上
on a planet in a glacial age.
不知道“女性”这个词意思的男性人形生物
The male humanoid who doesn't know the meaning of the word "female".
斯科提：舰长！
SCOTTY: Captain!
过来这里，长官
Over here, sir.
里面有食物和其他东西，是我们肌肉发达的朋友的仓库
There's food in there and other stuff. A storehouse for our muscular friends.
我不那么认为，斯科提
I don't think so. Scotty.
金属，锻造过，回火过
Metal, forged. Tempered.
这些不是我们的“聪明”朋友做的
Our apish friends didn't make these.
你怎么看？
What do you think?
可能是为了让那些生物远离食物
It could be to keep those creatures away from the food.
或者食物可能是其他人为了吸引他们来这里设下的诱饵
Or the food could be a lure set by the others to bring them here.
- 那么光束可能是个信号 - 这个洞穴就是个陷阱
- Then the beam would be a signal. - And this cave a trap.
如果它给其他人捕捉生物，它不也会捕捉我们吗？
If it traps the creatures for the others, won't it trap us too?
没错
Exactly.
- 柯克呼叫企业号 - 企业号，我是乌乎拉
- Kirk to Enterprise. - Enterprise. Uhura here.
立刻把麦考伊传送下来
Have McCoy beam down immediately.
你和警卫留在这里，我们会保持联系。
You and the security team will remain here. We'll be in constant contact.
是，长官
Aye, sir.
好的，老骨头。带上他
All right, Bones. Bring him along.
让他走在右边
Keep him close to the right.
准备好了？
Ready?
[当当响]
[CLANG]
呼叫 契科夫让他把我的胃送下来
Call Chekov and tell him to send my stomach down.
可能要等很久。我们不妨舒服一点。
It might be a long wait. We may as well be comfortable.
相位枪击晕模式
Phasers on stun.
在上面接收到的能量离我们越来越近了
That power we picked up above. We're getting closer.
- 很多？ - 足够把这颗行星推出轨道
- A lot of it? - Enough to push the planet out of orbit.
- 来源？ - 直径100英里的核反应堆，或者...
- What source? - A nuclear pile 100 miles across, or...
- 或者什么？ - 离子能
- Or what? - Ion power.
我们在减速
We're slowing down.
- 她还好吗？ - 我马上让她开口
- Is she all right? - I'll have her talking in a minute.
你不属于这里，你不是莫格人
You do not belong here. You are not Morg.
- 负责人呢，带我去见他 - 他？什么是他？
- The one in charge, take me to him. - Him? What is him?
你把史波克的大脑怎么了？它在哪儿？
What have you done with Spock's brain? Where is it?
你不是莫格或伊莫格人。我不知道什么大脑
You are not Morg or Eymorg. I know nothing about a brain.
- 你说谎 - 她没有。读数没有变化
- You're lying. - She's not. No change in reading.
她不知道
She doesn't know.
看看你的通讯器能接收到什么信息
See what you can pick up on your communicator.
我们不想伤害你
We don't want to hurt you.
这是什么地方？
What is this place?
这个地方就是这里
This place is here.
- 你是谁？ - 我是卢玛。我是伊莫格人
- Who are you? - I am Luma. I am Eymorg.
你不是伊莫格人。你也不是莫格人
You are not Eymorg. You are not Morg.
你是什么？
What are you?
吉姆
Jim.
你从她那儿了解不到信息。这是一个孩子的思维
You'll get nothing out of that one. Hers is the mind of a child.
我有一些头绪，但我无法完全理清它。
I've got something but I can't quite get a fix on it.
史波克[通过广播]：真有意思，活动没有尽头，但也没有意志
SPOCK [OVER RADIO]: Fascinating. Activity without end, but with no volition.
- 史波克，是你吗？ - 柯克舰长？
- Spock, is that you? - Captain Kirk?
是的，史波克
Yes, Spock.
您的声音绝对令人愉悦
There is a definite pleasurable experience connected with your voice.
- 你在哪儿？- 麦考伊医生，你和舰长在一起吗？
- Where are you? - Dr. McCoy, are you with the captain?
- 我还能去哪儿? - 史波克，你在哪儿？
- Where else would I be? - Spock, where are you?
还有史考特工程师? 不幸的是，我不知道我在哪里
Engineer Scott as well? Unfortunately, I do not know where I am.
我们会找到你的，不会很久的
We'll get to you. It won't be long.
可行的想法。看来我不太可能找到你了
Practical idea. It seems unlikely that I shall be able to get to you.
快点
Quickly.
她在这里。就是她。你对史波克的大脑做了什么？
There she is. That's the one. What have you done with Spock's brain?
柯克：舰长日志，星历5431.5
KIRK: Captain's log, stardate 5431.6.
在与史波克的大脑接触后
After making contact with Spock's brain,
麦考伊，斯科特和我被囚禁在一个高度复杂的文明中
McCoy, Scott and myself were taken prisoner in a highly complex civilization
在西格玛龙系六号行星的地下几百米处
hundreds of meters below the surface of planet Sigma Draconis VII.
上面的原始生物
The primitive creature above
警告过我们关于痛苦和喜悦给予者
warned us about the givers of pain and delight
以及被他们俘虏的可怕后果。
and the frightening consequences of being captured by them.
你是什么？你为什么在这里？
What are you? Why are you here?
你有话要说吗？
You have something to speak?
- -史波克的大脑在哪儿？ - 我们不认识史波克
- Where is Spock's brain? - We do not know Spock.
这是史波克，你在飞船上见过他，你拿了他的大脑
This is Spock. You saw him on the ship. You have his brain.
必须给他装回去。你把它怎么了？
It must be restored to him. What have you done with it?
你和卢玛说了大脑的事，但我们不明白。
You spoke to Luma of brain but we do not understand.
我不认识卢玛，但我在企业号上见过你
I do not know about Luma, but you were on the Enterprise. I saw you.
- 我们不知道这些事... - 你来到我的船上
- We do not know these things... - You came to my ship.
我们只知道下面这里和上面这里。这是我们的地方
We know only here below and here above. This is our place.
- 你不是莫格人， 你是陌生人 - 我在我的船上见过你
- You are not Morg. You are stranger. - I saw you on my ship.
吉姆
Jim.
她可能不记得或者真的不知道，分离可能是完全的。
She may not remember or really know. Disassociation could be complete.
看起来她似乎不可能给史波克做手术。
It doesn't seem possible she could perform surgery on Spock.
- 是的，不可能 - 你伤害了卢玛
- No, it doesn't. - You hurt Luma.
不允许再伤害任何人。
It is not permitted again to hurt anyone.
对不起，我们不想伤害任何人。
Sorry. We don't want to hurt anyone.
如果你想回家，你可以走了。
If you wish to return to your home, you may go.
不，我们要留在这里了解你
No. We'll stay here and learn about you
告诉你我们的故事。
and tell you of us.
是的。比如说，上面是寒冷刺骨的。
Yes. For instance, above it's cold and harsh.
下面是温暖的，空气清新。
And below, it's warm. The air is fresh.
是的，没有太阳，但有光。
Aye. There's no sun but there's light.
我想和负责人谈谈。组织者，管理人员
I wish to talk to those in charge. The organizers, the managers.
- 你们人民的领袖 - 我就是领袖，没有其他人了。
- The leader of your people. - I am leader. There is no other.
不可能，谁造的机器？
That's impossible. Who built the machines?
- 谁是医生？- 谁控制这个？
- Who are the doctors? - Who controls this?
控制？
Control?
- 控制员？ - 是的，控制员。
- Controller? - Yes, the Controller.
控制员。控制的人？我想见他，见他。
The Controller. Who controls? I would like to meet, to see him.
不，这是不允许的。绝不允许。控制员是单独的，分开的。
No, it is not permitted. Never. The Controller is alone, apart.
我们为他服务，任何人不得靠近。
We serve him. No one is permitted near.
- 我们没有恶意 - 你们是来毁灭我们的。
- We intend no harm. - You have come to destroy us.
- 我们想谈谈史波克的大脑 - 大脑? 什么是大脑？
- We want to talk about Spock's brain. - Brain? What is brain?
- 它是控制员，不是吗? - 是的。在某种程度上，它是。
- It is Controller, is it not? - Yes. In a way, it is.
人类大脑控制着个体的功能。
The human brain controls the individual's functions.
老骨头，斯科提
Bones. Scotty.
史波克的大脑在控制
Spock's brain controls.
这不可能
It's not possible.
伟大的...领袖
Great... leader.
伟大的领袖，我们从遥远的地方来向你们的控制员学习
Great leader, we come from a far place to learn from your Controller.
你撒谎，你认识我，你是来带走控制员的
You lie. You know me. You came to take back the Controller.
他是我们的朋友，你必须带我们去见他，我们求你了
He is our friend. You must take us to him. We beg you.
- 不快点就晚了 - 不要把他们带到控制员那儿
- Soon it'll be too late. - Do not take them to the Controller.
- 他们会被阻止的 - 你必须带我们走
- They will be prevented. - You must take us.
我必须学会怎么做，跟我来
I must learn what to do. Come with me.
- 你要把他们留在这里 - 是的，主人
- You will keep them here. - Yes, mistress.
苏鲁：舰船日志。苏鲁中尉记录
SULU: Ship's log. Lieutenant Sulu recording.
我把企业号控制在西格玛龙系七号的轨道上
I'm holding the Enterprisein orbit about Sigma Draconis VII.
柯克认为史波克的大脑在这个星球上的直觉似乎是正确的
Kirk's hunch that Spock's brain is on this planet appears to be correct.
契科夫留在地面上，负责联络舰长和企业号
Chekov remains on the surface to liaise between the captain and Enterprise.
我从来没有过那样的感觉，我身体的每一根神经都在燃烧
I never felt anything like that. Every nerve of my body was on fire.
我不敢相信一个人能忍受这样的痛苦
I wouldn't believe a human could take such pain.
这些东西要保留一段时间，一定是某种磁性锁。
These are on to stay for a while. Must be a magnetic lock of some kind.
怪不得莫格人如此顺从... ... 而且害怕
No wonder the Morgs are so obedient... and terrified.
我们见过的原始思维是如何维持这个地方运转的？
How is this place kept functioning by the primitive minds we've met?
那些女人永远不可能建立起这么复杂的东西
Those women could never have set up anything as complex as that.
这需要工程天才，但那些女人身上没有这样的迹象
That takes engineering genius. There's no sign of that in those women.
她们足够聪明，发明了这些装置来控制男人
They were smart enough to invent these devices to control men.
- “痛苦和快乐” ，他在上面说 - 你已经注意到快乐的方面
- "Pain and delight", he said up above. - You've noticed the delight aspect.
我当然注意到了这些令人愉快的方面
I certainly noticed those delightful aspects.
- 那也是女人的命令 - 史波克的大脑和这个有什么关系？
- That too was commanded by women. - How does Spock's brain fit into this?
有了通讯器，我们也许就能找到答案
With a communicator, we might be able to find out.
这个家伙让我们无法接近
This fellow is keeping us from our property.
- 难道没有办法纠正吗？- 科学可能会提供答案。
- Isn't there a way to correct that? - Science might provide an answer.
- 确实，舰长 - 同意，医生
- It does, Captain. - Agreed, Doctor.
- 科学会胜利的 - 起来，斯科提，老骨头？
Science will triumph. Come on, Scotty. Bones?
给他们一些东西，让他们在外面待一会儿。史波克？史波克？
Give them something to keep them out a while. Spock? Spock?
来吧，史波克
Come on, Spock.
- 史波克，你在这个频率上 - 史波克：是的，舰长，我还在这里
- Spock, you were on this frequency. - SPOCK: Yes, Captain. I am still here.
你回到企业号了吗?
Have you returned to the Enterprise?
不，我们也许能找到你
No. We might be able to locate you
如果你知道他们利用你的目的。
if you knew what they were using you for.
- 是医学上的吗？- 我不确定
- Is it medical? - I'm not certain.
我似乎有一个伸展到无限远的身体
I seem to have a body which stretches into infinity.
身体? 你什么都没有。
A body? You have none.
那我是什么?
Then what am I?
- 你是个没有实体的大脑 - 真有意思
- You are a disembodied brain. - Fascinating.
这可以解释很多事情，医生
It could explain much, Doctor.
我的延髓在努力工作，呼吸，泵血，
My medulla oblongata is hard at work breathing, pumping blood,
维持正常的生理温度
maintaining a normal physiologic temperature.
- 我们没时间了 - 你为什么要拿自己的生命冒险
- We don't have time for that. - Why are you endangering your lives?
我们是来送你回去的，你在哪里？
We came to put you back. Where are you?
- 回到哪里？- 回到你的身体里
- Back where? - Back into your body.
- 我们把它带来了 - 想得真周到，舰长
- We brought it along with us. - Thoughtful, Captain.
但可能不切实际。虽然我相信医生能取出碎片,
But probably impractical. While I might trust the doctor to remove a splinter,
但我不相信他有修复大脑的知识
I do not believe he has the knowledge to restore a brain.
- 谢谢 - 无意诋毁
- Thank you.
- No denigration intended.
这种技术在银河系还不存在
That skill does not yet exist in the galaxy.
有移除它的技术。就有修复它的可能
The skill to remove it exists. Restoring it must also be possible.
- 所以我们必须找到你 - 我很感激你所冒的风险
- That's why we've got to get to you.
- I appreciate the risks you're taking.
但只有在有机会成功时，它们才值得。
But they are worthwhile only if there is a chance for success.
- 已经过了多久了？- 18小时12分钟
- How much time has elapsed?
- 18 hours and 12 minutes.
麦考伊肯定告诉过你，24小时是我身体的极限...
McCoy must have told you 24 hours is the maximum my body can be...
- 我告诉他了 - 还剩5小时48分钟
- I told him. - That leaves five hours and 48 minutes.
时间似乎太短，不够培养出这种技能，不是吗？
It does seem all too brief a time to develop such skills, does it not?
是的，非常短。这就是为什么我们必须马上找到你
Yes, very brief. That's why we must get to you immediately.
给我们发个信号，我们就能找到你了
Beam us a signal so we can home in on you.
收到
Got it.
有个问题。我们身上有疼痛装置。怎么把它们弄下来？
One question. We've got pain-giving devices on us. How do we get them off?
我会给它最高优先权
I shall give it top priority.
我有一个答案。你们的疼痛带是手动控制的
I have an answer for you. Your pain bands are manually controlled.
手镯上的红色按钮能打开它
The red button on a bracelet releases them.
我知道这没有多大意义
I know that does not make much sense.
是的
Yes, it does.
集中注意力，史波克，集中注意力，史波克
Keep concentrating, Spock. Keep concentrating, Spock.
一定在这里，舰长
Must be in here, Captain.
史波克，不痛了
Spock. No pain.
没有
No.
走开
Go away.
我们都会死的，你不能把控制者带走。
We will all die. You must not take the Controller away.
控制者是年轻和强大的。完美。
The Controller is young and powerful. Perfect.
- 史波克：真是受宠若惊 - 你会给我们一万年的生命
- SPOCK: How very flattering. - You will give us life for 10,000 years.
- 再找一个控制者 - 旧的已经完了
- Find another Controller. - The old one is finished.
- 一万年内都不会有 - 史波克，你在一个黑盒子里
- There won't be one for 10,000 years. - Spock, you're in a black box
与光线捆绑成一个复杂的控制面板。
tied in with light rays into a complex control panel.
- 真有意思 - 你说你还有呼吸，
- Fascinating.
- You say you're breathing,
泵血，保持体温
pumping blood, maintaining temperature.
有没有可能你在循环空气
Is it possible that you're recirculating air,
运转供暖设备，净化水源？
running heating plants, purifying water?
毫无疑问这是我所做工作的一部分
That is unquestionably part of what I'm doing.
- 他必须留下，他必须留下！- 他不会留下的。
- He must stay. He must stay! - He will not stay.
你拿走了他的大脑，你要把它放回去，你原来是怎么做的？
Now you took his brain. You will put it back. How did you do it?
- 我不知道 - 她不能
- I do not know. - She couldn't.
她的思维运作很简单。官能也几乎萎缩了
Her mind is functioning on a simple level. Faculties are almost atrophied.
一定是她干的，你怎么做到的？
She must have done it. How did you do it?
- 这是古老的知识 - 你怎么学会的？
- It was the old knowledge. - How do you get it?
- 我把“老师”戴在头上 - 什么是“老师”？
- I put on my head the Teacher. - What is the Teacher?
所有古老知识的老师
The Teacher of all ancient knowledge.
请允许我解释一下，她指的是这个地方建造者的知识
If I may explain, she refers to the knowledge of the builders of this place.
我扫描了一下，一个令人印象深刻的仓库
I scan it. A most impressive store.
- 它是怎么运作的？给我们看看 - 我不能。
- How does it work? Show us. - I cannot.
- 你必须告诉我们 - 我不能
- You must tell us. - I cannot.
只有通过古人的命令我才能理解
Only by command of the ancients may I understand.
它是怎么工作的? 给我们看看，我们会保护你的
How does it work? Show us. We'll protect you.
它是一种装置，可以为女祭司领袖的思想提供馈电回路。
It is a device with feeding circuits to the mind of the priestess leader.
它的使用是由建造者严格预先确定的
Its use is strictly predetermined by the builders.
不，这知识是被禁止的。我不能知道秘密！
No, the knowledge is forbidden. I must not know the secrets!
我会受到惩罚的！
I will be punished!
先生们，控制者对“老师”的功能的解释是正确的
Gentlemen. The Controller's explanation of the Teacher's function is correct.
但是他不相信我
But he gives no credit to me.
我提供知识使用的方法
I provide the means for the knowledge to be used.
- 没有我... - 就没有微妙的奇迹
- Without me... - There can be no delicate miracle
能让史波克的大脑活着
that kept Spock's brain alive.
谢谢你，医生。你真是太仁慈了
Thank you, Doctor. That was very gracious.
是的，从一开始我就很欣赏你的能力
Yes. From the very first, I appreciated your ability.
很好。那你也会明白，如果没有老师，
Good. Then you will also appreciate that without the Teacher,
我就没有知识来使用你所提供的知识
I would not have the knowledge to use what you have provided.
相位枪设定为致命
That phaser is set to kill.
确实如此。这就是你带给我的知识。
So it is. That is the knowledge you have brought me.
别动。如果你的武器杀人，它就会杀了你。
Do not move. If your weapon kills, it will kill you.
我们不是第一个带来杀戮知识的人。但你会杀死史波克
We're not the first to bring knowledge of killing. But you will kill Spock.
控制者死了？控制者可以活一万年
The Controller die? The Controller will live for 10,000 years.
我们要把我们的忠诚献给他
We shall give him our devotion.
但是史波克会死的，他的身体现在就要死了
But Spock will be dead. His body is dying this minute.
你不明白吗? 我的人对他们的控制者的需要
Do you not understand? The need of my people for their Controller
比你对你的朋友的需要更多
is greater than yours for your friend.
任何人不得杀人，不得为任何目的杀人，这是不可宽恕的
No one may kill a man. Not for any purpose. It cannot be condoned.
不要
Do not.
我不会杀人，我也不想杀人
I do not know killing. I do not wish to kill.
[斯科提呻吟]
[SCOTTY GROANS]
- 必须遵守戒律 - 你必须帮助我们
- The commandment must be fulfilled. - You must help us.
当你来到船上的时候，你有知识，但在这里，你没有
When you came to the ship, you had the knowledge. But here, you didn't.
- 对的 - 这种知识能持续多久？
- Correct. - How long does the knowledge last?
- 你们的三个小时-时间刚刚够
- Three of your hours. - That's just enough time.
如果你有这方面的知识，你能恢复你拿走的东西吗？
If you had the knowledge, could you restore what you've taken?
- 我不会 - 你必须帮助我们。
- I would not. - You must help us.
你必须用这种知识来恢复你所夺取的东西
You must restore with that knowledge what you have taken.
- 不 - 你必须把你拿走的东西放回去
- No. - You must put back what you took.
我不会背叛我的人民，控制者会留下来
I will not betray my people. The Controller will stay.
对她有用，也许对我也有用
It worked for her. It might for me.
她是个外星人，她的大脑结构不同
She is an alien. The configurations of her brain are different.
这可能会对你的人类大脑造成无法弥补的损伤，医生
It could cause irreparable damage to your human brain, Doctor.
我是一名外科医生，如果我能学会这些技术，我可能会留住它们
I'm a surgeon. If I can learn these techniques, I might retain them.
那样你也可能失去医生
You might lose the doctor that way.
可能会。但如果我不试试的话我们肯定会失去你
He might. But we're sure to lose you if I don't try.
你不能为了我拿自己的生命冒险
You cannot jeopardize your life for me.
史波克，你没听到吗？
Spock, didn't you hear?
我也许能够保留并将这些技术带给世界
I might be able to retain and bring these techniques to the world.
难道不值得冒这个险吗？
Isn't it worth that risk?
难道你不坚持自己承担这样的风险吗？
Wouldn't you insist on taking such a risk yourself?
去吧，医生。带上“老师”
Go ahead, Doctor. Put the Teacher on.
不！
No!
当然
Of course.
一个孩子就可以做到。一个孩子就可以做到
A child could do it. A child could do it.
柯克：舰长日志，星历5432.3
KIRK: Captain's log, stardate 5432.3.
麦考伊医生正在修复史波克的大脑
Dr. McCoy is proceeding to restore Spock's brain.
我们的问题是: 我们不知道他增长的知识能持续多久
Our problem: we do not know how long his increased knowledge will stay.
任何进一步使用这种教学设备的尝试都是不可能的
Any further attempt to use the teaching device is impossible.
这会要了他的命
It would kill him.
我从没见过这样的情况，他正在以曲速进行手术
I've never seen anything like it. He's operating at warp speed.
我想亲自试试那个“老师”
I'd like a try at that Teacher myself.
他会回到你身边，我们也会被毁灭
You will have him back and we will be destroyed.
你不会的，你将第一次失去你的控制着
You won't be. You'll be without your Controller for the first time.
- 但你们会过得更好 - 我们会死的
- But you'll be better off. - We will die.
你会得到你应有的发展，所有这些本不该属于你们
You'll develop as you should have. All of this shouldn't have been done for you.
现在下面的女人和上面的男人将一起控制
Now the women below and men above will control together.
- 没有痛苦他们是不会帮助我们的 - 还有别的办法
- They will not help us without the pain. - There are other ways.
你们会发现他们的，你们必须搬去地表
You'll discover them. You must move to the surface.
- 在上面我们会死于严寒 - 你们不会的
- We will die above in the cold. - You won't.
你们将学习建造房屋，保持温暖，工作
You'll learn to build houses, keep warm, to work.
我们会帮你一段时间
We'll help you for a while.
人类在更恶劣的条件下生存下来，这是进化，你会没事的
Humans have survived under worse conditions. It's evolution. You'll be fine.
柯克舰长！
Captain Kirk!
- 怎么了? - 他正在遗忘
- What is it? - He's forgetting.
- 我不能，我... - 老骨头？
- I can't. I... - Bones?
老骨头？
Bones?
所有的神经，有成千上万个，我该怎么办？
All the nerves. There are a million of them. What am I supposed to do?
我该怎么办？
What am I supposed to do?
你现在不能停下来
You can't stop now.
我正在用大锤穿针
I'm threading a needle with a sledgehammer.
我该怎么办？我不记得了
What am I supposed to do? I can't remember.
- 我不记得了 - 老骨头？
- I don't remember. - Bones?
- 没人能修复大脑 - 你可以
- No one can restore a brain. - You could.
不久前，这还只是小孩子的游戏
A while ago, it was child's play.
柯克：舰长日志，补充
KIRK: Captain's log, supplemental.
我们拯救史波克生命的赛跑可能是徒劳的
Our race to save Spock's life may have been futile.
麦考伊忘了从“老师”获得的知识
McCoy has lost the knowledge from the Teacher.
他一直在利用自己的技能试图继续手术
He has been drawing on his own skills in an attempt to continue the operation.
但是他犹豫不决，不确定
But he is faltering and uncertain.
希望他能借助史波克的大脑寻求帮助
In the hope he can draw on Spock's brain for assistance,
我指示麦考伊优先连接史波克的声带
I instructed McCoy to give priority to connecting Spock's vocal chords.
- 怎么了？- 他快死了，我无法阻止
- Well? - He's dying and I can't stop it.
史波克：是的
SPOCK: Yes.
- 麦考伊医生？- 史波克？
- Dr. McCoy? - Spock?
如果你把我的语言中枢重新连接好，我也许能帮上忙
If you finish reconnecting my speech center, I might be able to help.
语言中枢
Speech center.
是的
Yes.
没错
That's correct.
一件一件来
One thing at a time.
[清嗓子]
[GROANS]
这样好多了，医生，试试声波分离器
That's better. Now, Doctor. Try the sonic separator.
声波分离器...
Sonic separator...
我已经有一些感觉了
I already have some sensation of feeling.
刺激神经末梢，逐个观察反应
Stimulate the nerve endings and observe the reactions one by one.
探针正确时我会告诉你
I shall tell you when the probe is correct.
然后，你使用三激光连接器密封
You will then seal using the tri-laser connector.
三激光连接器
Tri-laser connector.
- 准备好了吗? - 好了
- Ready? - Ready.
右手食指
Right forefinger.
正确
Correct.
右...手腕
Right... wrist.
正确
Correct.
右手肘
Right elbow.
正确。非常好，医生
Correct. Very good, Doctor.
我永远过不去这个坎儿了。这个瓦肯人在告诉我如何操作。
I'll never live this down. This Vulcan is telling me how to operate.
- 完成了 - 怎么样？
- Closed. - Well?
我本可能犯一千个错误。
I could have made a thousand mistakes.
密封神经末梢。加入神经节
Sealing nerve endings. Joining ganglia.
液体平衡是正确的，但我不知道
The fluid balance is correct, but I don't know.
恭喜你，医生。谢谢。
Congratulations, Doctor. And thank you.
- 你觉得怎么样？ - 总的来说，我很健康
- How do you feel? - On the whole, I am quite fit.
这真有意思。倒退文明的一个杰出例子
This is fascinating. A remarkable example of a retrograde civilization.
巅峰时，超越我们的能力
At the peak, advanced beyond our capabilities,
现在在这个原始水平上运作
and now operating at this primitive level.
这一切都始于几千年前，当时冰川时代再次出现
And it all began thousands of years ago, when a glacial age reoccurred.
这个体系是为女性建造的。男人留在上面
This complex was built for women. Men remained above.
发生了男女分裂。一个有意思的文化发展...
A male-female schism took place. A fascinating cultural development...
- 我不该做的 - 做什么？
- I shouldn't have done it. - What's that?
我不该重新连接他的嘴
I should have never reconnected his mouth.
好吧，我们冒了风险，医生
Well, we took the risk, Doctor.
正如我所说，这是一种多年未见的文化发展
As I was saying, a cultural development that hasn't been seen in ages.
最近一次发生在旧地球上，当时罗马人...
The last such occurrence took place on old Earth when the Romans...